Tony Fast (he/they):
Well, welcome everybody.
Today we're going to get
started with our, how to build
inclusive data experiences event.
Our featured today is Frank
Elavsky.
we'll have
him
go on and about a half an
hour or so in the short
term we wanted to just kind
Tony Fast (he/they): of set
the stage for the event.
Isabela, if you can go to the
next slide.
One of the oh, I see
what happens.
I get the delay.
All right.
Okay.
So since we are doing and building an
inclusive, talking about an inclusive
event, first thing y'all need to be
aware of is there is a code of conduct.
This is a Project Jupyter event,
which means that we're abiding the
Project Jupyter code of conduct.
If you have any questions
or anything that you need
to report.
you can
click on this
link and follow any
instructions. if
you need to contact any of the event,
organizers Isabela,
myself
and Tania are all here to
support you.
so please
use the chat and
let us know if anything, if there's
anything you need. be reminded,
this event is recorded and posted
publicly.
so
between
discussions and chats and stuff
like that, all of this is public.
So, you know, be mindful,
, and yeah, that's
all the
business kind of stuff that we need.
So what happens next in this?
I think we talk, we're going to Jupyter.
Oh my God.
Everybody is a jovyan.
Yes, you are new people.
There's
new life.
But yeah, so this event is
sponsored by Project
Jupyter which is
an all in one
data science data analysis solution.
And we do a lot of data
visualization You're going
to hear a
lot of terms during the course of
this event that probably
Tony Fast (he/they):
revolve around Jupyter.
You'll hear about Jupyter notebooks.
You'll hear about JupyterHub.
You'll hear about JupyterLab.
If you're unfamiliar with Jupyter,
please ask questions in the
chat while this is going on.
I think it would be good to take a little
poll about how familiar folks are with
Jupyter so we can kind of get a feel
for that.
, and,
yeah.
Welcome to possibly your
first Jupyter event or your
10th hundredth Jupyter event.
But we're happy to have you here.
I want to go next.
Parts of this slide.
Didn't love.
I've never gotten that before.
Perfect.
Yeah.
Right.
So Jupyter is more than a single
project file type
Tony Fast (he/they): interface.
It probably is the community at its
extent, but Jupyter
Tony Fast (he/they): has
a lot of things going on.
There are a lot of tools that enable data,
ingest data, visualization, data analysis.
So this talk that we're having today
is really important and recording.
It will be super valuable to the community
at large.
so again,
Tony Fast (he/they): if anybody
is not familiar with Jupyter,
please let's use the chat.
We've got a bunch of Jupyter experts
here that can help answer your
questions.
We're kind
Tony Fast (he/they): of going
to have an intersection of
Jupyter experts and accessibility
experts and design experts here.
So let's try and make
the best of all of these
different people meeting.
I think
my only job
was to talk about Jupyter, but
it's really important to recognize
that Jupyter does have tons of data
visualization libraries, and it will
be fabulous for us in this room.
And those that hear this talk to figure
out how to apply Frank's principles
and the things that he talks about to
our open source tools so that we are
building a more inclusive experience.
Why don't we keep on cruising?
And I think it's
time for Isabela
to tell us
a little bit about accessibility.
Isabela Presedo-Floyd (she/her):
Yes, it is.
And real quick.
Hello.
I am Isabela Presedo-Floyd.
I am a Latina woman with short
curly black hair, and I'm just
wearing a cool black and white
blazer today who you heard talking
was Tony.
and that
Isabela Presedo-Floyd (she/her): is, I
don't know how Tony wants to describe
himself, but he's my partner
Isabela Presedo-Floyd (she/her):
in crime in Jupyter.
So I'm just going to be giving an overview
because I don't know exactly what Frank
has to give to us today in terms of like
explaining accessibility or anything
else, but just making sure we're all
kind of starting on an even foundation,
whether you decided to join this event.
Cause you're like, wow, accessibility.
I already do a ton of that and I
want to learn more. Or whether you're
like, oh, I've never heard of this.
I'm just really curious about what it is.
So accessibility is we're going
to be using it today is a term to
describe designing building and
just creating things that can be
used by as many people as possible.
But specifically we're focused on making
sure that disabled people can use it.
Right?
These are people that we leave
out a lot in these processes
and in the things that we do.
And just abled.
A lot of times people will focus on
blind and visually impaired exclusively.
So I also want to say, that's
not the limit here at all.
Could be motor disabilities could be
cognitive, could even be temporary.
There are all kinds of situations where
you're like, things may be changing.
What we're going to be
talking today though.
More because Jupyter is a web app
is digital and web accessibility.
So you'll probably also hear the
words with WCAG at some point or a
WCAG the Web Content Accessibility
Guidelines because
those are the major guidelines
used for this type of content.
And other than that, I
think we're good to go.
Are you seeing anything in the chat
Tony that I should be addressing?
Are we getting a lot of people
saying that they are new to this?
Not anything like that.
Tony Fast (he/they): It doesn't seem like
there's any questions, but if anybody has
any, please feel free to throw them out.
I can't find the poll. Did
we, did we put out a poll?
There it is.
How do we
show the results?
I click on show results.
There we go.
We've only gotten one vote.
So only one person heard of Jupyter.
Those that are
in hopin right next
Tony Fast (he/they): to
the chat.
, there is
Tony Fast (he/they): a
little tab for polls.
We'd love if y'all could let us know
some of your experience with Jupyter so
we can gauge this a little bit better.
Isabela Presedo-Floyd (she/her): Okay.
Yeah.
And we're exploring this
whole interface too.
So thank you for going
along in that ride with us.
And I'll probably ask you a few
more times since I can't see it
while I'm screen-sharing Tony, but
yeah, that's my quick overview of
accessibility.
One of the
Isabela Presedo-Floyd (she/her):
other things I want to say,
though, accessibility is not new.
Right.
I personally seen an uptick in interest
in it recently, which is awesome.
I love to see that, but I think it's
important to remember that this isn't
something that just appeared or that
people haven't been working on, or that
hasn't been a problem for a long time.
So just to point out a few
instances that might be familiar.
I am in the U.S. size looking curb
cuts, meaning the kind of ramps in
sidewalk curves, which was initially for
wheelchair access have been happening
in the U.S, since about the 1940s, even
though they were not required at that
time, national legislation starts to
become a little more common globally.
So multiple countries between
like the 1990s to the 2000, and
we've had some version of web
accessibility guides since 1995.
So these aren't things that have
come up overnight, and there's a
lot that we can learn from our past.
However, this is kind of new to Jupyter.
There have been people talking about
accessibility for several years,
but it's been really a challenge
to get a concerted effort as it is
with anything open source, right?
There's a lot of back and forth
they're working on volunteer time.
So it makes sense, but we're
really trying to ramp that up
and we have a lot to learn here.
So that's part of why we're doing these.
Accessibility is also cross project in
Jupyter.
I spend
Isabela Presedo-Floyd (she/her): a
lot of time in certain projects, so
I wanted to make it clear, you know,
this touches all kinds of things.
One of the things, I mean
by this, is that right?
It's not just about the
notebook file or the interface
or the documetation or
Isabela Presedo-Floyd (she/her): the
organization website or any of that.
Right.
It's actually all of it at once.
And so it's not just one project
problem or one person's problem
or even one team's problem.
These are cases where we need to
collaborate and do what we can to do
solutions that can help each other.
And that can carry over, right?
Like if we can do something that
solves it for multiple projects
at once, that'd be awesome.
One example of this in case you're
new to Jupyter, I'm going to explain
this kind of interconnectedness
and JupyterLab, because that's
where I spend a lot of my time.
So say we're starting with the notebook
file, which is a totally separate thing
used by a lot of different interfaces.
And if
you add Lumino a different
Jupyter project and a bunch of other
things you can end up with Jupyter
Lab in interface for the notebook.
You also
have the documentation with
this, right?
So we've already talked about like
three different Jupyter projects.
And on top of that, we have
RetroLab, which takes Jupyter
Lab components, pulls it apart a
little and uses kind of the most.
But I want to say like the
most foundational ones.
And so we have kind of
the stripped down version.
Now we're at four projects and
of course someone could actually
ignore JupyterLab entirely and
just be working with a notebook in
so many more notebook interfaces.
And then we have a whole bunch of others.
So that is just one small section of
the ecosystem to give you an example
of how this, how this works and why we
are looking for accessibility solutions
that can cover kind of all of these
pieces, all of these Lego blocks.
As I'm showing here to train,
give that idea, Legos will never
stop being a good metaphor.
It's kind of amazing.
Accessibility is also
happening now, right?
This is not something that
we just want to talk about.
We are making some progress,
some highlights from the past
year because we've had really
awesome community members.
We've had regular meetings for a year,
which has just been great for keeping
touch for helping one another, like
people saying, I need to know this.
I need to know.
We'd also like community growth.
Like we've had a lot more people
show up to these meetings, a
lot more people bringing ideas.
Some people I've never met in Jupyter
before even we also had a WCAG-based
audits of multiple projects with
related issues and PRS on GitHub
so that we can track the problems.
And we can also track what's
works, has been done to fix them.
And we have a CZI Essential Open
Source Software for Science grant.
We have one for Jupyter accessibility
at the moment, which is awesome
because that funding allows us to
pay people to work on this as their
job and not just rely on volunteers.
We have had some really amazing
volunteers and I'm super grateful,
but this is, this is a big project.
So it's wonderful to have
a little bit more going on.
I think that's oh, no way of future goals.
So some other things they're working
on that haven't been touched on
yet automated tests, big thing,
and open source projects, for sure.
And we really need them with Jupyter
to avoid our work
being undone.
We need to make sure that the notebook
file format is accessible as can be, as
I kind of showed with those Legos, right?
That's the foundation of so
many different projects and
even things outside of Project
Jupyter.
And we need
Isabela Presedo-Floyd (she/her):
to update
improve the documentation,
both
making the content more accessible
in the format that it's coming in.
Of course, we also want to
get you more involved, but
we'll get more on that later.
There's tons of opportunity if you end
up in joining today's event and yes,
that's what I have to say it for now.
Thank you for that overview.
I will be able to stop sharing
my screen and be in chat now.
So if you have any questions,
I'll do my best to answer them.
And I am here to pass it over
to Frank Elavsky, a man who
Tania is going to introduce.
Yes.
Tony Fast (he/they): Wait let's take a,
let's just take a quick delay real quick,
but there are a bunch of people, pretty
much everybody here has heard of Jupyter.
So we're good on that.
I think we're going to have another
poll coming out just to find
out how people are feeling about
accessibility.
The two
Tony Fast (he/they): things that
we're putting together here.
So beyond look out in the chat for
that poll.
, and,
, Tony Fast (he/they): thank
you all for the introduction.
And then I'm going to send
it back over to Tania.
Tania Allard (she/her): Hi,
y'all I am Tania, my pronouns.
Are she/her and I am a Latina woman.
With short purple hair and I'm
wearing a black t-shirt
purple headphones and black
glasses.
It's an
honor to
introduce our next speaker, Frank.
I am so, so, so
excited
about his
presentation,
Frank, for those of you that don't know,
Is a software engineer, returned
researcher, and his currently
pursuing a PhD at the intersection
of accessibility and information
rich systems and Carnegie Mellon.
He's also the author of an amazing tool
or library, called Chartability, which
helps us to actually to build more accessible
data, experiences, graphics, and such.
And he'll be talking more about all
of his fabulous work and research.
And I think this is the perfect
timing to bring Frank onto
the stage.
Frank Elavsky (he/him): Hey everybody!
My name is
Frank, pronouns.
He/him. I am a masculine
white man with
my hair, pulled back in a bun and I'm
wearing a gray turtleneck.
Frank Elavsky (he/him):
I'm also in a weirdly lit
room.
So I'm doing
my best with lighting
situation here.
I had to
move here because
like the neighbors on the other side
of the house are doing construction.
So this is the
quietest room.
Yeah, super
glad to
be here.
I just want
Frank Elavsky (he/him): to,
before I begin, give a massive
shout out to the folks who have
already spoken and,
Frank Elavsky (he/him): the folks
who have already done work in
order to just make this happen.
I was, you know, Isabela reached
out to me a months ago and said,
Hey, would you like to speak?
And as I've been preparing
materials, I went and dug, I, I
wanted to know what is Jupyter
actually up to what's this
Frank Elavsky (he/him): community doing?
And I was honestly
surprised lots of
Frank Elavsky (he/him): advocacy work.
That's
exhausting work, really,
and lots of trying to
Frank Elavsky (he/him): get
organized.
I noticed
Frank Elavsky (he/him): there's even
an audit that I like it's, you know,
at least a link I think a student
did and I kind of combed through
that and I'm really impressed.
I think there's also a lot of
accessibility that already has like work
that already has been done at least,
you know, from me poking under the hood
and digging around in some notebooks.
But at the same time, I think
there's a lot of opportunities.
And so today I'm going to be talking about
things that advice.
Frank Elavsky (he/him): So my
own experiences working in open
source communities, working with
accessibility,
and also specifically dealing
with the complexities with what
I'm calling our data experiences,
the complexities that data
experiences offer and the
challenges making these
things
accessible.
So yeah, I
think that, that's sort of
the intro that I wanted
to give.
Thanks again for setting
me up and for bringing
me here.
I'm really
excited.
Tania Allard (she/her):
Okay, fabulous.
So we are going to leave the stage
for Frank and he's going to be taking
questions, at the end of the presentation.
So if you have any questions, feel
free to type them on the stage chat
and we'll pass them off to Frank.
So we'll see you a little bit.
Frank Elavsky (he/him): Great.
Let me get my screen up
and I'm going to make sure
I share my system audio.
Okay.
It looks like we're
live.
So message.
Frank Elavsky (he/him): Thank you so much.
All right.
What do I do?
I kind of
have been intro'd already, but
I'll just talk about, I think
these parts of my background are relevant
for today.
I'm currently
Frank Elavsky (he/him): actually
researching what I'm calling data
interaction or accessibility and
information, rich systems and
go back and forth and exactly
how I want to talk about it.
The work that I do, I want to encompass
the actual, I want to address
Frank Elavsky (he/him): what I
largely refer to as communities
who do data work, and I want to
make that work more accessible.
So not just for people who
are an audience member or a user of a
chart or graph or interactive data system.
But also I want to make the work that
people do more accessible
as well.
So that's my research focus. In
the past,
and I currently
organize a group called
DataVizA11y, where a group
of people who do accessibility work
specifically for data visualization.
We're all volunteers
we've been meeting for two
something years.
We do little
Frank Elavsky (he/him):
projects together on
the side.
Lots of advocacy work.
We partner
Frank Elavsky (he/him): with the
Data Visualization Society if
anybody's familiar with them.
So really
big org.
That's like
Frank Elavsky (he/him): a,
you know, collection of like
20,000 practitioners across
the world.
I also do
Frank Elavsky (he/him):
industry consultations.
So between just these things, my hands are
full often.
My industry
Frank Elavsky (he/him):
consultations include like auditing
engineering and all kinds of
stuff for you know,
big companies
out there.
Sometimes
Frank Elavsky (he/him): it's volunteer
work, but most of the time it's not.
And previously I was a staff engineer
on Visa data experience team.
And on the right, we see a bar chart and
this is an example chart component that
we made.
And we did
Frank Elavsky (he/him):
a design systems work.
So if any of you are familiar with
what that kind of work entails, that's
what we did.
, and,
Frank Elavsky (he/him): yeah, I was the
lead on the accessibility efforts there as
well as you know,
Frank Elavsky (he/him): one of
the main engineers on the project
for all kinds of other stuff, too.
And of course, as already
mentioned, I authored Chartability.
So in my own work, in the data
experience space I recognized
Frank Elavsky (he/him):
that there were a lot.
Things that were unaddressed
or ambiguous in web standards,
which isn't the fault web
standards.
Right,
it's just
Frank Elavsky (he/him): a
recognition that the work of
accessibility is always
ongoing and changes
Frank Elavsky (he/him): often,
depending on our context, in the
way we use technology and in the
space of charts and
graphs
we needed a new set
Frank Elavsky (he/him): of
heuristics for testing accessibility.
And so I looked at research, I looked
at standards and I looked at communities
of practice to see what are people
already doing and already have opinions
on and what are some needs out there.
And then I collected all of this into
a set of tests.
Frank Elavsky (he/him): It's
kind of an auditing system.
So we'll talk more about that later, but
that's me.
So yeah,
Frank Elavsky (he/him): my passion is
obviously specifically, not just like
making data work accessible, but it's like
charts and graphs and data visualizations.
We generally refer to them.
As on the screen here, I've
demonstrated on the left.
We have a bar chart that kind of scales
with negative bars up to positive
bars, and it ranges in color from red
on the left, and it slowly becomes
yellow, then a light blue and then to
a dark blue and with the scaling color,
we also have textures lines on these
bars that are changing in angle and
thickness to redundantly
encode the
color scale.
That's a
Frank Elavsky (he/him): technique for
low vision.
And then
Frank Elavsky (he/him): on the right,
there's a really interesting
screenshot.
This is from an audit of like a red
arrow pointing into a pie chart that is
labeled Google and the rest of ad tech.
And then a big screenshot that
is a contrast checker, noting
that the pie chart has a contrast
failure.
So yeah, before
we start this,
this may be, accessibility
and especially attending
an accessibility
talk may be new to some of you.
And I just want to strongly stress,
please share screenshots of this talk
and get you know,
Frank Elavsky (he/him):
conversation going.
But when you do, if you share screenshots,
make sure you add alt texts very
important.
I think
Frank Elavsky (he/him): almost every time
I've given a talk, there has been one
person who has tagged me in a post without
alt texts.
, please don't be shy.
, I don't
Frank Elavsky (he/him): want
to discourage you from sharing.
I really hope that you do.
In fact you know,
Frank Elavsky (he/him): you all
can just get started, screenshot it
right now.
, and
, Frank Elavsky (he/him): already
defined or already
Frank Elavsky (he/him): kind of unpack a
little bit is like, what is accessibility?
And I kind of want to, I want to talk
really briefly about two ways we use
the word accessibility
Frank Elavsky (he/him): or accessible
or access.
, and I also
Frank Elavsky (he/him): want to note
that if you ever see a 11 Y sometimes.
Allie. ally, eleventy like a nightmare
pronunciation that abbreviation
represents accessibility because
accessibility as a
word has the letter, a 11 letters and the
letter Y , I don't
know why we chose this as
a community, but
this, that, that little abbreviation
is how we also refer to it.
So there's two definitions working
definitions that are
important to talk about.
There's one, which is the broad definition
of accessibility, where we say, you
know, it's, it's about the qualities
that make an experience open or usable to
all people.
And that's
Frank Elavsky (he/him):
like general access, right?
So we have technological access issues.
Like there are access
justice issues for people who
don't have, fast
bandwidth,
internet connection, or any
internet at all.
That's an
Frank Elavsky (he/him): access justice
issue, but we also have accessibility
issues specific to people with
disabilities.
And we want
Frank Elavsky (he/him): to, we, we're
going to be working mostly in that second
definition, which is where we're defining
it as the knowledge and skills to break
down barriers specifically for people with
disabilities.
So I want to say that this
is maybe my
favorite graphic that I throw all around
all the time, because it, it does one
thing that is powerful when you're
communicating disability, which is.
We're going to
kind of expand people's
paradigm of how we think
about what
disability is.
I've got
Frank Elavsky (he/him): a graphic
here and it's got, it's kind
of represented like a table.
It has columns and rows
Frank Elavsky (he/him): and on each row
is a, is a functional type of disability.
So they're labeled touch,
see, hear, and speak.
And
then the columns are actually
Frank Elavsky (he/him): temporal
dimensions of disability.
So how disability affects
different people depending on time.
So some people have a
permanent disability.
And for example, on the
touch column, that's
Frank Elavsky (he/him): somebody
who just only has one arm.
Some people have a temporary disability.
And so then there's a person
who just has an arm injury.
That means their arm, hopefully,
will heal and then they will
have access to their second arm.
And then there's
situational, considerations.
Frank Elavsky (he/him): And in the
final column for touch,
Frank Elavsky (he/him): you
might have like a parent holding
a child. And
when we think of
something like a curb cuts, which we've
already talked about in a curb cut, we're
designing for you know,
Frank Elavsky (he/him): originally
advocacy was done on behalf
and with, and by people who
use wheelchairs, but it turns
out that cutting
Frank Elavsky (he/him): curbs and building
ramps helps people with temporary and
situational limitations
Frank Elavsky (he/him): as well.
So there's kind
of this this way
that I want
to frame disability, where we think
about the challenges that people with
disabilities face as things that we could
also face and maybe also often face.
So the way that I phrase
this is I don't
want to
say that we're like we are disabled
constantly by environmental variables.
We can be.
The right way to talk about this, as
we've all already experienced a disabling
limitation at some point in our labs, even
if it's just temporarily or situationally.
And that means that accessibility,
the work of, of making things
accessible is personal to
all of us.
Absolutely,
number one, most
important thing to
consider for data
visualization is that virtually
everybody it is, we
have a very, very high rate
of losing
our visual acuity as we age.
And this is just part of aging.
Everyone will face this and it
is massively important for the
field of data visualization.
So it's not, we're not just
considering we're helping
other people who are
low vision.
No, it's very likely going to be
us when we age we're going to need
access.
So I see some
Frank Elavsky (he/him):
great things in the chat.
I may have suffered temporary
or situational this morning.
Yeah.
One of the things for me, it's, if I
have to like kind of pitch to somebody
really quickly, I show them something I'm
like, oh, I had this really great thing.
I want to show you on my phone.
And I try and do this outsider
and a bright location.
And I give them my phone and my contrast
is intentionally as low as possible.
And they're like, I can't, what,
what are you trying to show me?
And I'm like, oh, sorry.
And I turned the contrast
up and then they can see.
And it's just a way to frame
the fact that our environment
participates in disability.
Right.
And this is why it's important to
think about the environments we
built as participating in disabling
experiences and limitations for
other people are rebuilding an
environment that is potentially
causing some limitation
for someone else's access.
That's really, really, really
important.
Also can
Frank Elavsky (he/him): someone,
I think we started with.
At off time.
Can somebody tell me when, what
time will the 30 minute mark
be from the start of my talk?
Just drop it in private
chat or the comments?
Sorry about the
interruption.
Like, are
Frank Elavsky (he/him): we
running until 30 after right now?
Is that what I'm supposed
to be totally done?
I want to make sure we
have time for questions.
I actually have questions for the
community.
And then
Frank Elavsky (he/him): I hope
to also receive questions.
I think that's good.
Okay.
So great.
I'll keep
rolling.
Sorry.
So
Frank Elavsky (he/him): intention
with everything I just said, right?
Keeping in mind that
we can be experienced
Frank Elavsky (he/him): like disabling
limitations or temporary limitations.
I just want to say.
The specific barriers that people who
live with disabilities or have permanent
disabilities, the barriers that they face
can't be substituted by our experiences.
So just because we can put on
a blindfold and pretend to be
blind, that absolutely does not
mean that our experience
Frank Elavsky (he/him): of
simulating or experiencing
temporary disabling
Frank Elavsky (he/him): limitations
is in any way the same as the
experiences that actual people with
disabilities face.
So something
that I like
to do is just kind of frame the
relevance from a data perspective,
especially when I talked to data people,
they love numbers.
So we're
Frank Elavsky (he/him): just going to go
through some numbers.
The
Frank Elavsky (he/him): world
health organization recognizes
that, you know, globally
vision is a significant like a
global health issue , uncorrected
Frank Elavsky (he/him): or uncorrectable,
moderate to severe visual impairment,
which we kind of loosely refer to as
low vision, depending on who defines it
affects , near.
30%
Frank Elavsky (he/him): of people
globally.
A lot of
Frank Elavsky (he/him): that is
preventable by healthcare,
Frank Elavsky (he/him): but what
we're looking at today is just
from a pure numbers perspective.
Low vision
Frank Elavsky (he/him): considerations
for accessibility are one of the most
important things we can do to improve
global access to our interactive
systems.
And the
graphic that
I'm showing here is just an example
of a set of bars that are very low
contrast on the left using light gray.
On top of the other light grays, the
text is light gray on black or on white.
And then to the right is just
a use of much darker gray for
the text.
And
then a dark gray
on white instead
of light gray on light gray.
So improving the way
we design color and
contrast is hugely important.
Plus other techniques for local.
Motor impairment and
functional disability.
This is big.
So just in the United States alone,
motor impairment and functional
disability can, you know, it affects
between 13 and 15% of people.
This is self-reported data from the CDC.
So, you know, a lot of our data
visualization interaction paradigms
use a mouse like you're hovering
on things you're clicking, right?
We are very
mouse driven people in
Frank Elavsky (he/him): analytical
spaces, but a lot of people
who have motor impairments
or functional
disabilities use assistive
technology like switches
or keyboard
interfaces to interact
with things and
almost everything from, from a technical
perspective uses what's
Frank Elavsky (he/him): called the
keyboard API or the keyboard interface.
So we need to make sure that
our mouse driven interactives
are also keyboard accessible.
This is hugely
important
access issue also cognitive
and attention
impairment.
You know,
Frank Elavsky (he/him): this includes
ADHD, autism a wide range
Frank Elavsky (he/him): of other,
you know, intellectual, developmental
disabilities, wide range of
other things affects
Frank Elavsky (he/him):
between 11 and 13% of all
people.
And you know,
Frank Elavsky (he/him): we really have
almost no guidance on how to have, we have
this huge potential, right in interactive
systems, interactive technical systems to
scale, or let user set their preference.
How much explanation do you want?
How much clarity do you
want in text, how much text
you want?
And I think
Frank Elavsky (he/him): that
there's a huge potential for
our field to kind of explore
how can we you know,
Frank Elavsky (he/him): convert
complex language into plain
language.
What can  we do to to make
more
accessible data experiences
Frank Elavsky (he/him): for, for
these folks?
And deep in
Frank Elavsky (he/him): my talk.
I just want to like revisit data
visualization.
Now that
Frank Elavsky (he/him): you've
kind of seen me throw data,
visualization data experiences.
Haven't actually said data representations
yet that sometimes at this point in
the talk I've mentioned it, but I'm
talking about data visualizations
because this is the field that
I've worked in for a long time.
And I'm really equipped, I think,
to engage a lot of
Frank Elavsky (he/him): the issues in
this space not just
Frank Elavsky (he/him): from an
accessibility standpoint, right?
Like I'm a data vis
practitioner, so I can refer
to myself.
So data
Frank Elavsky (he/him): visualization,
sometimes abbreviated data is with a
Z or data is with an S is presenting
data in a structured symbolic.
And the structure and semantics
of these things, we create
actually go far beyond the visual.
And so I prefer to call these data
experiences or representations because
that's a little more inclusive when
we're trying to do inclusive work, right.
We should use inclusive language
and talking about experiences or
representations is a little more of
an accurate way to talk about the work
we're really doing under the hood to make
something say, screen reader accessible.
Well, you know, the person with a
screen reeader may or may not even
see the, the
Frank Elavsky (he/him): chart, but they're
going to be perceiving the underlying
structure of it as they interact with it.
And that, that different type of
perception is you know,
we need to be able to talk about it
more than just what the word
visualization.
I love this
demo.
Sarah's a very good friend of mine.
Somebody who I respect
greatly, they recorded
themselves.
They audited a
bunch of
election
graphics,
which are, it's important data, right?
We need to make sure that data
about our elections, especially more
and more we've been representing
them in charts and graphs.
We need to make sure that
they are, they're
Frank Elavsky (he/him): accessible.
So this is, you know, just one of many
experiences that Sarah captured of
what it's like for somebody who uses a
screen reader on their mobile device to
interact with a a map, an
election map. Linked video: image,
image, image, image,
image, image, image, image.
Frank Elavsky (he/him): I'm going to
pause it here.
So
we just Sarah is
just swiping and
the keyboard focus, which is this kind of
white outline around each state is moving
between states, which is fascinating.
Somebody did the work of making
keyboard.
Or you know non mouse
driven access work, that
technicality, that
functionality is there under the hood,
but what's missing quite importantly, is
all the data about what each state who did
Biden or Trump, win the
state? Is it a win, is it a lead?
Is it a flip what's, what's the status?
And what's even the state.
What state are we currently
on as we navigate?
So really important data itself.
I always say this data is really painful,
but visualization shouldn't be right.
The whole point of visualization is
kind of it performs
this
other task.
And why
Frank Elavsky (he/him): am I talking
about data visualization and not
like just broadly data stuff like
notebooks?
Well I already
Frank Elavsky (he/him):
sort of spoiled it.
It's like my specialty,
my field,
but also
Frank Elavsky (he/him): this
is where I like to reframe how
we think about visualization.
Visualization is actually
already in assistive
technology.
When we
Frank Elavsky (he/him): take data,
something that's hard to understand
and we turn it into a representation
or experience, that's easier to
understand that is an assistive
act.
Right?
And we are already building
assistive technology.
So my challenge then is to everybody.
Why, why do we
stop there?
I think
datavisualizations are really
helpful starting
point because we're already kind of
trying to break down cognitive barriers.
And then my main question
is just why not stop?
Why not keep going?
Why not continue to do what we're
already doing
and try
and make stuff
that's really difficult, not quite as
difficult?
And, and
ultimatelyaccess is about
breaking down
barriers and assistive
Frank Elavsky (he/him): technology is an
attempt to you know,
overcome barriers using
technology.
So I want us
to continue this
work and When I frame
things with data representation
and data
experience I'm talking
about, because
we're using this, this new inclusive
language, we're going to be talking about
like functional parts of visualization.
Like, how does it work when you
interact with it in different ways,
semantically, what does it mean?
What are we talking about?
What's a bar on a
bar chart?
And, and
how do points
on scatterplots relate to each other?
Are there
outliers?
we're also
talking structurally, like how have we
prepared this data to be,
navigated or experienced?
Frank Elavsky (he/him): Is it tabular?
Is it non tabular?
Is it nested or
hierarchical?
And then
also when we're thinking
about interactivity,
both kinds of interactivity, right?
Like.
Interacting using a keyboard to
navigate interacting by like,
you know, selecting something,
but also interactive experiences.
Like you get in a notebook where you put
in code, you get some kind of output,
that's an interactive experience, right.
That's a loop.
And so when
we talk about
data representation and data experiences,
we're actually encompassing like the
whole picture of what it means to interact
with data.
And so here's,
here's a question I have for everybody,
which is and we'll
Frank Elavsky (he/him): spend
a couple of minutes on this.
Please put, put your answers
in chat, try and have somebody
in mind who asks
you this question.
Not me, but somebody, right.
Somebody you really want to convince.
And they say, how can we make open
source data work more accessible?
Maybe there's somebody really important,
or somebody with a lot of power or
somebody who's funding, something
you have like one to two sentences to
like, just say, like, here's my answer.
Here's what
we can do.
Throw it
in chat.
I really just want to see
what everybody's ideas are.
And maybe some of you will have
good ideas that, you know, these
are things we actually should say.
So I've got the comment screen
open, please drop this you're
answering chat.
Frank Elavsky (he/him):  So there
are a couple up in the thread.
Oh yeah.
Cause I asked it earlier just
as a test of the chat system.
Hmm.
Thank you.
Established channel for feedback.
Hm.
Cameron also said something.
Yeah.
Great.
So I'm just going to speak
these out loud while folks still
try and add their own input.
Okay.
So
starting all the
way back, Anette said first thought
established channels for feedback
from folks with disabilities, as
they say nothing about us without us.
Cameron:
I am, I'm newer to data work, but perhaps
even some simple things like making sure
there's good documentation and
making sure visualizations
are accessible as a start.
Yes.
Love that.
Let's see,
make it part of a standard review
process that was Isabela posting
as Tania, then Cameron said, make
sure that we use the tools we use
to do data work are accessible.
Annette said, figure out how to
enable sonification. Peyton educate
the broader community. More training
on how to make data work accessible.
R Ely said include accessibility,
best practices in tutorial
instructions. Gabriel: hire people,
but maybe in tension with open source.
Yes, that is a huge tension in
open source.
Thinking about the practice
known as dog fooding.
Oh, I don't know what that is.
Might when we get to open
discussion at the end, it might
be great to hear more about that.
Rose create a system of questions
or considerations to iterate through.
Hmm.
That's good.
Mars:
Agree on making
accessibility part of review.
Yeah.
Part of the cultural expectation.
I like that.
That's been said twice now.
Yes.
Okay.
Tania: sort of a chicken and
egg, but also making sure our
communities are more inclusive.
Oh yeah.
That is the big chicken and
egg problem in communities.
It's like, it's like there was a
community organizing meeting that
I went to, where they were trying
to, like, they had identified
members of the community who had
mobility , disabilities
and the building that everybody was
meeting in was not accessible.
There was
no ramp.
Rose more
specific improved
command line, terminal interfaces.
Ooh,
interesting.
I'm really interested.
I think
maybe that could be an interesting
discussion later.
Most folks I know who are blind or low
vision and use a screen reader actually
prefer command line interfaces to every
other kind of graphical user interface or
anything else.
because
to them it's just
pure text.
But I'd
love to normalize no mouse days.
Yes.
I love using no mouse.
Okay, cool.
That's,
Frank Elavsky (he/him): that's plenty.
That's a lot.
I hope you
Frank Elavsky (he/him): all
keep this conversation going.
And I think we had some
really good answers in here.
I was wondering if anybody would
try and be super ambitious and big
and some of these are big, but I
would actually say you all did a
good job of keeping these winable.
These are things you could really
do.
And now I'm
going to kind of dig into, I have
a background in
community organizing, and I have some
advice that I want to give to you all.
So here's like 10 strategies.
I'm going to talk a little more
about the first four, and then
I'll just let you have that kind
of structural advice for your own
stewing.
But,
let's break into the things that
you as an individual can do.
Four things that I think
are really good to keep
in mind on the quest
for
accessibility.
I just want
to preface that not all action is
solved by individuals alone.
And
in fact very little
is especially
if we're really thinking about how
connected we are to our work and our
environment.
So much
of what we do is dependent and
interactive
with others.
Especially
in open source.
So I'm always, always, always
keep in mind the structural
picture of, of things
that are
happening beyond just
you as a person.
And the first thing I want to say
is, you know, learn how to evaluate,
I've been in this space for a very
long time, check out Chartability.
If you haven't check out WCAG, which
is Web Content Accessibility Guidelines,
just kind of learn. Like don't reinvent
the wheel.
And you
certainly don't
want to invite people with disabilities
to kind of help you in your quest.
If you haven't done what
I consider to be the
bare minimum, which is
evaluate your own systems and
try and, you
know, meet a decent standard of
access according to those
standards.
That's step
one.
This is my itself,
quite a long quest.
So but get started.
And I'd
love feedback on Chartability too,
as you all interact with
it, more and more folks using it would be
really helpful because it's an open source
project too. This next
one is huge and open source.
The tension is like you're
trying to do everything for free.
And often people with disabilities
are asked to do work for free
too much.
Cause everybody
wants them.
So one of the best pieces of advice that
I have is obviously invite people to join
you, but also just find where they're
already talking about stuff like Liz Hare.
I love Liz.
Liz is amazing, really
outspoken.
Has a
lot of interesting things to say on
Twitter.
Really outspoken
in the R
community and. So find
where they're already speaking, right?
Like that's a way to help them
avoid like doing redundant work.
They're already doing the work
of trying to educate people.
So like go to wherever they're at
and just join their communities.
It doesn't have to be Twitter,
you know?
There are
lots of places you
could go.
Another
thing that I want to say is pace yourself, work
on just a single new thing at a time.
I have done this.
And honestly, I think it's the only
way I've survived certain periods
of my life on the quest towards
anything but especially accessibility.
So right now I'm like digging into like
touch and keyboard interaction, paradigms.
Thinking about how we structure data to
like, make those interaction paradigms,
like really seamless and powerful and
empowering.
And that's
just where I'm at right now, digging
into these issues.
So like even, even me, I'm always
working on just one thing at a time.
And if you overwhelm yourself with
trying to solve all of accessibility
at once that's not that's not
sustainable for an open source
community, right?
The advantage of open source is that
if you're going to do one thing, you're
going to really hope that somebody else
is going to be doing their thing too.
And if we all do that, there might be
a chance to really engage something
at scale with a bunch
of broad and difficult problems.
And then this one, this is, this is
really from my community organizing
background, which is break issues
into smaller, manageable parts.
I found an
audit online of,
I think a student did have something
in Jupyter and it's great.
It's like a full WCAG
audit, but there's a lot in
there.
And , I would
say that if you ever end up
in a situation
like this, try and break anything
into the smallest pieces you can so
that you can get small wins quickly.
That is so important in open source
and especially volunteer communities
because people will burn out
otherwise.
And you
know, I, I think that broadly
the organizing
community has a lot
Frank Elavsky (he/him): that could
teach us about open
source work that we really, you
know, most open
source communities don't pay attention
to, but especially with something
important and related
to justice,
like access you know,
Jupyter has has a chance
to negotiate access in a way that
like Plotly couldn't right.
You all are the platform that most
people come together on to do their work.
And say, for example,
you just had, you know, a
really simple requirement
that, you know, libraries need to be
able to provide like, need you need.
Be able to provide a way for
users to add alt text to all
of your charts and graphs.
That's not
a problem we want
to solve.
You need
to be able to do it and here's when
we need it by or something.
I don't know.
I don't know if that's actually winnable,
but it's an example of like one small
thing then you can do as a community with
your power.
So yeah.
And then
there's structural strategies.
Maybe just take a screenshot of
this, save it, stew on it later.
I'm not going to like kind
of walk through all of this.
The first five are like really common
to like strategies for implementing
accessibility and organizations.
And I would add,
I added number six because
it's important for
volunteer and like open
source work, which is celebrate your wins.
Like very intentionally.
So like, I hope that by the end of today,
everybody, except the people who organized
all of you, it's your job to put together
an event where you thank the people
who have done all the work until now.
Like, please, please,
please celebrate them.
Like learn their names, send
them emails, thank them for what
they've done.
That is
hugely important because burnout is,
is real and it is so
stressful.
Anxiety inducing. The pressure
is real in this work and people
who are doing
the work you know,
celebrate them and celebrate
yourself too for what you've
done.
So I think
let's see
for the sake of time, I'm gonna
maybe like, just briefly talk about
evaluation because
I think it's step one.
It's what everybody
should learn.
And then we'll just
Open things up
for discussion with the time we have
left.
So learning
how to evaluate
is something that anyone can do.
You can be a designer, you can
be an engineer, you can be an
analyst an auditor.
Obviously auditors
audit, right?
But even
managers, everybody should have like an
instinct.
And you
get instincts like that looks
like it's low contrast.
You get an instinct like that when you
just have a set of standards that you
regularly rely on and, you know, right?
So you got to build that system, or
you've got to build that knowledge and
experience in order
to be able to just have an instinct,
I can look at something
now and say that it looks low contrast.
Let's, let's
check it.
And,
looking to standards is the best first
step, because standards are
going to be consistent, right?
Standards change very slowly.
So it's a good step one for
evaluating.
I always
talk about how, you know, thousands
of years ago, people
use stilled wood fasteners, or like
screws by hand, and none of them were
interchangeable.
They would
break down easily.
It takes forever to build and
data visualization is like that.
It takes a long time to
build a lot of stuff.
What we do from scratch is from scratch.
It feels pretty flimsy, but
when you look the standards
like the Phillips screw standard
revolutionized
fasteners
as an industry and it enabled us to
have automobiles
and a whole bunch of other things, right.
You can go to a hardware store and get a
Phillips screw and you expect it to work
pretty well.
And I want
that for data
visualization, at least at a low level.
And especially for things
like accessibility, I want an
accessible, interchangeable
experience across across environments,
across the world.
And in order to get there, we
all have to get on the same page
with how we're evaluating things.
So look at
WCAG, if somebody
hasn't dropped the homepage and
chat the link
for just Web Content Accessibility
Guidelines, that'd be great.
Just drop it in.
It informs policy by
governments that you know represent
like more than half of the world's
population.
So it's and it's
anticipated to be adopted at a
policy by
2025, I think 90% of the world's
population.
So like,
yeah, at least get on the same
page with WCAG.
And then there's tons of
research that shows that what
WCAG does not go far enough.
Right?
And talk to anybody who's
interacted with a compliant system.
Who's disabled, they'll
have feedback still.
Right.
So after you do your due diligence, this
is the last note I really want to end
on, which is please involve people with
disabilities and yes, you should probably
pay them.
I know that's
in tension with open-source, but you have to
incentivize things even in an open source
community and. and
try and make it
fair.
So I have some
advice on making your collaborative
collaborators lives
easier, then I'm just going to breeze
through number one, invite
them to
discussions.
Number two, find
where they're at
enjoying them.
That's powerful.
Frank Elavsky (he/him):
Not for many people
do that.
Three: try
and write up issues on your repo with
them or for them.
Don't always just expect like people
to come to you with problems, like be
proactive empower
them
to help drive design
decisions that affect them.
So if you're like, Ooh, we have this tough
issue with low vision, do you want to
help us?
That's powerful
if they
get to be a
co-designer right.
And then if you're
Frank Elavsky (he/him): going to
pay anybody in the whole process
of open source, I like to just argue
you pay people with disabilities
because their expertise is very rare.
It's very demand.
And from a justice perspective,
they're often, far too often
asked to do things for free.
I am asked to do things for free all
the time and my disabilities.
I navigate
through life.
So I'm always thankful
when people compensate
me for work or for speaking or for
anything.
I'm hugely
grateful
for that.
But everybody's
going to have a different level of
commitment and experience and
expectation and
starting with you know,
a standard.
A rate that you hope to pay people
before you talk to them and offer
that upfront is the best way
to do it.
So that
you don't expect them to
ask you.
And then
the last advice I have is try to
use what
already exists, both to integrate
into your own work, but also just as
inspiration, the number one place
I always point to is Highcharts.
I, I
love them.
Oystein
is a good friend and you know, his
work with Ted
at Elsevier, they have created what I
think is one of the most impressive and
accessible libraries
out there for doing data visualization.
And you can just go
to their accessibility
page and just dig into the richness
that they have
to offer.
So that's it I forgot
to send slides.
So I think I
emailed Isabela
right before my talk started.
And hopefully we can get
the slides to everybody.
I don't know how
we put up put up
stuff, but yeah, it'd
be great if you could all get the
slides so you can
get the resources and stuff and that's
it.
Thanks.
Tony Fast (he/they): Frank, that
was, that was incredible.
Frank Elavsky (he/him): Thank you
so much.
Tony Fast (he/they):  It really
reinforces how important the advocacy work is.
Like you definitely left with things that
organizations can take and really empower
accessibility.
Thank you
so much right now.
Let's take some questions.
I hope you all
have been hanging
out, getting ready for
this time.
If you want
to throw your questions into
the chat you know praise and
kind words will also find their way
there that we
can share.
But yeah,
Isabela, I'm
curious while we're
waiting for questions to roll in,
are there
any questions that came to mind
to you while you were watching
Frank's talk?
Isabela Presedo-Floyd (she/her):
I mean, yes, but I'm trying
to filter what's useful.
I know
one that brought
up kind of at the end was about
specifications.
Right.
Which is something that's on my mind a
lot, because especially with, I am, since
I'm not really a code contributor to open
source projects, I'm not the main one.
What am I going to say?
I'm not going to be the main one,
writing the guts of the things.
And so it really matters to me trying
to set up something so that people
can figure out what they need to do.
Right.
And that's how I see specifications too.
So with that, I guess I would want to ask,
like, what, how do you prioritize that?
Right.
You have Chartability kind of
has a specification going on.
How do you sort those things?
How do you prioritize things?
Frank Elavsky (he/him): Good
question.
So 18F is
a government agency and they
actually have
like this super rad like list of
like accessibility priorities.
So if you want to like offload
prioritization to somebody else, like
look at what they, how they prioritize.
The, the reason I say this big is
because when you make question,
you make a decision about
priorities especially
in the
accessibility space,
it's, it's
Frank Elavsky (he/him): difficult
to be fair and know what's fair.
And I point to 18F because
they're a government agency,
a lot of decision-making
went into their own list of
priorities.
So for like
specifically web
content they have
like a great breakdown.
I would all tab and go find it, but
maybe somebody can go quick and drop it
in chat.
But
also another thing that you should keep
intention with like a
priorities list that's like,
top-down is always allow the community
to disrupt your priorities.
If somebody comes to you and they're
like, Hey, I need this thing.
And I'm like doing this
thing, honestly, like if
you have
like
an open source community in place
that can support feedback
like that.
And you
have bandwidth to flex, like help
people as they
come to you because that's powerful
and there's going to be traction.
Anytime a person comes to you
with an issue that you're not,
it's going to be hard to generate.
It's hard to generate traction
from your own list of priorities.
It's very easy to generate
traction when somebody comes
to you and is like, Hey, I need
this thing.
So yeah,
that's kind of my advice on that.
Isabela Presedo-Floyd (she/her):
That's yeah, that's really,
that's a good summary.
That
was
awesome.
Tony Fast (he/they): It looks
like we do have some questions or
comments.
Mars pjped in saying that she found
out about free pik through this talk.
So she's going to use those
stylish factors that people, but
I'm also going to share a post
that Mars wrote for Quansight Labs
about making NumPy accessible.
She's been doing tons of work on
NumPy's documentation,
making things accessible, and she
wrote a really rad blog post
as to why.
So that's,
that's gonna, that's shared in the chat
right now.
And then  let's see we got this
link to 18F shared.
I wasn't aware of that.
Thank you for bringing
that up.
Ely,
Ely ran an awesome accessibility,
community accessibility workshop
last year.
She said she's going
to be
using the argument that data
representation and visualizations is
already a form
of accessibility, which I kind of love
Frank Elavsky (he/him): Credit.
I'm going to type.
The very first person who coined
that is a super good friend of mine.
Probably.
I dunno, I don't want to be corny, but
maybe my best friend in this space.
His name is Doug
Shepherds,
he's been
in, he used to work at W3C.
He's been in web standards for years.
He's a data visualization guy.
He cares a lot about this stuff.
I don't know if he'll say this
out loud, but he's one of the
reasons we have SVG on the web as a
standard.
So I love Doug.
He's the first
one who I ever heard
say that statement and like, I
have workshopped
it a little bit into my own, like
how I like to phrase it, but yeah,
he's the inspiration for that.
I love Doug.
Tony Fast (he/they): That's great.
I, Frank, you
want
to take a have a look
at Annette's comment here.
I don't know if you want to add
any color to this about data
spatialization. Frank Elavsky (he/him): Yeah.
Yup.
I have a blind friend who refers to datavis
as spatialization
because the spatial component is
what he sees as distinguishing it.
I wonder what is the difference
between spatialization and
experiences, which is broader and
making me think, yeah, super good
question.
I am, I come
from, because I come from the
visualization community.
When we talk about a spatial
visualization, to me that is actually
different than something that might be an
abstract or , geometric-
only kind of representation like
a bar chart.
We wouldn't say it's spatial because
the bars don't represent real space.
They represent
abstract space.
And so it's
a symbolic representation of something
that's
not like out there in the world, but a
spatial visualization would be like a
map where the, the, the pixels or the
things you see on an X and Y coordinate
represents something real that's out there
or some approximation of the realness.
So when we say spatial, that's usually
how I refer to it is that there is a.
There's like a real thing out
there, but you know, what's
interesting that I think is
great about a blind
friend referring it to it as
spatialization
is when you work with a tactile
interface, it becomes spatial, all
abstract visualizations become spatial.
They become real things in reality
where their X and Y have like a
tangible meaning and existence.
So I think that that's fascinating.
I think that, you know, that's great
when I use experiences, that's my catch-
all for the most, the broadest way I could
possibly talk about what we do, which is
turning data into something. Representation
has, like data representation,
has this assumption that
the data is like trying to become
something, but
in experience is actually like framed
for you interacting with the thing.
Right.
And so I prefer to frame it that way.
Maybe it's to postmodern of me, but
when we come to data and we have some
kind of experience, that is the space,
it's very human-centered
that I
like to, that I like
to frame things around as opposed to data
representation, which is sort of framing
it around the data, not necessarily
the person first.
Tony Fast (he/they): That was beautiful.
Also, made me think of a tactile maps.
Frank Elavsky (he/him): Yep.
So they're the, they're the
oldest form of accessible stuff.
Perkins School for the
Blind has like a great
catalog.
So if you
have a blind friend who wants to go on a
pilgrimage to go to Perkins, they can
like check out and touch maps that
are like 200-something years old.
Tony Fast (he/they): Oh, that's so neat.
That's so neat. Data,
I mean, maps are,
the pioneering element data
visualization effectively, right?
Frank Elavsky (he/him): I think so.
Yeah,
absolutely.
Yeah.
Tony Fast (he/they): So we got
another, we got another comment
from Ely.
So,
we've been
running these I made,
I mentioned
these earlier to you, but we've
been running these low code
workshops that bring people
into the project, right?
We do acknowledge community's
important for accessibility.
One of the ones that's been great is we
can get people to edit RST and Markdown
and HTML and add some alt text to the docs.
But we've been hard pressed to find
some other places where people can
come in.
So we're
curious if you have any other ways
that you
can think about accessibility
being a door into the community.
Frank Elavsky (he/him): Yeah.
My favorite one to teach
people beyond alt text.
And by the way, if you
want to upgrade your alt
text game look into
image descriptions, which is the next level.
Alt text is a specific technology.
We use to provide an image
description to something, and alt
text is like behind the scenes.
Right.
But in image description more broadly is
also visually you can see the discriptive
of the image.
And I
think that when you
Frank Elavsky (he/him): look
into research by like the
Diagram Center their research
showed that providing visually a table,
you can see as
well as a summary is one
of the best things you could do for
accessibility, for
cognitive and vision-related impairments.
So yeah, if you want to like go next
level with just  alt texts, go to
image descriptions, which is like
kind of broader impacts more people.
But if you want something different to mix
things up teach people
how to analyze
contrast.
So you get
a little dropper tool, you dropper on
a color, you dropper
on the color that surrounds it.
You get a little contrast
ratio, like a rating between
the two.
And that's
a great way to give people that kind
of instinct
that when they look at something
they're like, Ooh, that looks a little
low contrast.
Can we bump that up?
Because we just need more people
aware of that because that I
argue that's number two, as
far as broad
impact behind textual
district.
Tony Fast (he/they): One of
the points I really loved when
you were talking was, you know,
learn how to audit your own stuff.
Right.
So last year during the event
that
Ely ran we had breakout
sessions where we
installed WAVE and
we had conversations
around learning how to use WAVE.
And, you know, it was a really nice way
from like almost a top-down experience
there, you know, you got, we wound
up talking about color, contrast and
navigability, but it's kind of a really
good, like splash into getting started.
So I'm going to just share
that WAVE extension on there.
I don't know if you have any
feelings plus or
minus on,
on WAVE,
but it's
Tony Fast (he/they): something
we've been advocating for.
Frank Elavsky (he/him): Yeah.
There's, my old
laptop actually crashed just earlier
this week, so I'm
using a new laptop or I'd pull up my
extension.
It's , oh, I forget
the name of it.
HTML something.
So WAVE catches, most things.
It's
pretty good.
I consider
it the
middle ground
of automated
Frank Elavsky (he/him): tools for the web.
What I think is the absolute best
is a little behind the scenes.
So it's not as approachable for everybody,
but it's axe dev tools. Axe, dev tools.
It runs in like you go to developer
tools and it'll be a tab there once
you install it without a doubt,
the best like their approach rules.
It's very good.
It's super
comprehensive.
So that's
at one end of
the spectrum, but on the
easy end of
the spectrum, and it's
something that catches things that
WAVE doesn't sometimes
is I think it's HTML code checker.
I don't know.
It's old, it's really old, but
it's good.
And it also
has some HTML standards that WAVE
doesn't, isn't necessarily
looking for
and it also
does a little better on SVG, so I
wish I could remember
it.
Sorry.
But yeah,
axe is my short answer, I guess.
Isabela Presedo-Floyd (she/her): Yeah,
definitely, definitely agree with axe.
I was going to say with, I mentioned
earlier, we were looking into testing stuff.
And that has been one of the main things
we've been trying to figure out how to
basically put all the things together.
There's a lot of good resources.
It's figuring out how they're going
to play nice with some of the,
yeah,
Jupyter stuff.
Tony Fast (he/they): Yeah.
Well, and it's so nice.
The Deque labs is open source and they
have their consulting service too.
Right.
So, you know, it hits that sweet
spot of what we're all trying to
do here.
So you
know, teaming up with other communities,
amplified each other's efforts.
Like I see writing tests as a future
opportunity, better test tools for
accessibility as a community opportunity.
Frank Elavsky (he/him):
We need that badly.
Right?
Like
the, the number one thing.
So we interviewed a lot of people
with Chartability
and like pretty much every single
accessibility expert who we interviewed
with Chartability, about Chartability,
who tried it out, said, okay, these rule.
And like half of these could be automated.
Like we need somebody to build that stuff.
And so, yeah, like even
just Chartability.
We, we could use, like, there's
a bunch of things that you could
measure.
And we aren't yet. As a note
about automated tooling, for those that
don't know, Deqie actually
did like a, an aggregate study of all
of their audits.
It's just like some
enormous amount of data.
And they found that in general,
automated testing, even the best stuff,
which is theirs, found finds about two
thirds of errors according
to standards, right?
So it's about 67% of all possible things
they found using automated testing.
And to take one thing, like imagine
a stacked bar chart, or like a tree
map, you've got a little subset.
Okay.
Here's the things automated
testing can confidently find.
That's a smaller set of all the things
that exist in standards and standards is a
smaller set of all possible accessibility
problems.
Right.
So somebody
did a study of just with blind people
back in like
2011, Chris Power and found, I think.
About that WCAG addresses is about
60% of the needs of people who use screen
readers and that's just screen reader use.
Right.
So think
of like automated
testing is just a little tool in your belt.
That's super helpful.
It saves you bajillions of hours of
time, but also definitely not the end game.
Tony Fast (he/they): Right.
This is, this has been such
a contention with our work.
Right.
Cause we've been going to a lot of
accessibility meetings and they're
like manual testing and it's like,
we know, we know, we know, but like
we're an open source project and
we're already getting some regressions
by not having automated testing.
Right.
So for us, like the automated testing
is also also a community contract that
helps us ensure that accessibility
stays there.
Gabriel
Tony Fast (he/they): had her,
oh yeah, go ahead, Isabela.
Yeah.
Isabela Presedo-Floyd (she/her):
I was going to say, I think the
process is a different expectation.
I think that they're totally right
about accuracy, but we can't actually
guarantee who or when or what
is going to be reviewed or how they're
going to review it on a open source
project has been the problem.
So yeah, that's, that's where I also agree
with Tony that I really think we need
some degree of automation just to catch
at all, but it is very tricky because
I worry about where that
puts us at the same time.
Frank Elavsky (he/him): Yeah.
One of the nice things about
automation in open source communities
is if you run a report and you
get, you know, 200 errors, some of
them may be opportunities
for new contributors who are ready to go
the next level and actually like dig
into code and fix some semantics or
something.
Because
it's not like, a lot of errors are
at the rendered HTML end.
They're not like under the hood,
you've got some logic issue
sometimes, but that's like
super approachable,
code-light.
Yeah, I,
definitely see a really important
role for automated
testing to play in open source.
Tony Fast (he/they): So,
so this this brings
another challenge
that we're seeing with Jupyter, which
is like a lot of these guidelines.
They're not for data
visualization right. They're.
They're not for web applications.
Right.
And we don't have a
normal website, you know?
So sometimes where we feel like
we're in uncharted territory.
Yes.
WCAG does continue to grow.
Hey, we get new color
contrast rules in a couple of
years.
Right.
Yeah,
Tony Fast (he/they): in the short term,
we might actually even have to start
going through, maybe even working a
little bit closer with Chartability and
thinking about this data experience.
Right.
Because it really be like, if
you're generating data, right.
Like if you walk into Jupyter and you're
like, I'm going to plot something, it's a
data experience that you haven't made yet.
Right.
And now you have to figure out
that whole path and journey to get
there.
And yeah, it's
Tony Fast (he/they): an
interesting challenge.
Isabela Presedo-Floyd (she/her): Let alone
can you get in the notebook in the first place.
Like, I
mean, you assumed that that
was possible,
Tony,
that's not always the case.
Frank Elavsky (he/him): I
definitely found when I dug
under the hood, one of the first things
I looked at was.
I think it was like selecting Python or
Python three, there was like a row of
square looking buttons and they are divs.
They are not buttons.
And they had like a tab index on
them and I'm like, Hmm, well, that's
just change that to a button you're
already more accessible, but yeah.
There's lots of little
opportunities everywhere.
Somebody.
Tony Fast (he/they): Yeah.
But wait, till you hear about the
head and keyboard manager underneath
of the whole thing. Isabela Presedo-Floyd (she/her):
I don't think we have,
there are some short, there are some
small wins.
And,
Tony Fast (he/they): you know,
one of the things that you
mentioned was making the problems smaller.
The cool thing about Jupyter is that it's
evolved into this pluggable ecosystem.
Everything's an extension, right?
Right.
So now we're able to focus on a more
paired down version of the newest Jupyter,
which is just the notebook experience.
Right.
You can actually take the same components
that we're building in JupyterLab,
improve JupyterLab's, accessibility, and
a simpler experience at the same time.
So we're starting to run into like the
super modular components and access
they're already internationalized, right?
So we have multiple languages and
coverage and multiple languages.
So now we have to go and do a
multi-lingual alt text and we have to
start making sure that this experience
is inclusive across nationalities too.
Frank Elavsky (he/him):  Yeah, I, I wanted
to say
that on.
So yeah,
that brings up a bunch of thoughts that
I have, but also other thoughts.
Oh, are we at time or.
I want to be respectful of everybody
here actually, before I keep
talking, what were we going to?
45,000.
Tony Fast (he/they): We're good.
Let's just, let's, let's continue
a conversation as long as possible,
or as long as you're up until like
about 10 or so, or the hour up into
the hour.
, and then
Tony Fast (he/they): we'll switch into
the breakout rooms and just spend the rest
of the time talking with the audience.
Frank Elavsky (he/him): Yay.
Okay, cool.
So I want him to
say that first off,
I love that both of you, Tony and Gabriel
have used
the phrase uncharted territory because
I it's very corny and I love it so much
because that's where we're at, right?
Like where, when you get into
accessible data experiences, it's
like it's uncharted space, right.
In both, both senses of
the word.
And on the
note about what
keg and I, I really,
really, really hope to frame standards in
the right way to folks, because
for me, this was difficult.
As, as a way of thinking about what
standards are for, I didn't really
realize it at first, but standards are a
political document. Standards
like, and that shapes how we should approach
them, right.
Standards are developed.
They are developed and adopted with
like political bodies influencing them.
Right?
So like the only reason standards
got adopted is because I think
there was early negotiations.
I think Japan really did a lot
of pushback against the U.S.
And then there were some
European players involved.
And so it became, standards are a
body of consensus before they are an
effective way of building accessibility.
Right?
Like the number one thing
you need to keep in mind is that standards
will never be fully sufficient
for creating accessible stuff.
It is simply a very good starting
point to bring people together for.
Talking about the same thing, because
otherwise it's just this nightmarish
mass of like, we don't know how to
measure things together and whatever.
So as long as you keep that in
mind about standards, that it's a
political document built
on
consensus that you know,
the real real quest for accessibility
is actually far
beyond that,
then you're
good.
And I also like to preface, like following
standards or meeting compliance is an
exercise in avoiding getting sued.
It's not an exercise in providing
a good accessible experience.
It's just a one step along the way.
Right.
It's just like trying to mitigate your
risk of like, you know, getting sued.
That's really the goal
it serves.
And if you
really want to do a good job of like actually
making an inclusive community
then yeah,
you're
going to have to go beyond standards.
And I
think that something
that is woefully under-discussed.
That is perhaps from my perspective,
the most hopeful thing about Jupyter is
what has already been mentioned, which
is that it's, it's within a modular
ecosystem.
And back in the day 12, 10,
12 years
ago now some really
great papers started to come out at
the intersection
of disability studies and assistive
technology where people started
to talk about what does it mean to
build communities where people can
self-advocate or where
people can, have
the
power to DIY their
own accessibility in real life.
We, people who are disabled,
we will often modularize our
own house.
Especially
if we have mobility
or like you know a physical
disability, we improve the world around
us, but our
technical systems are really surprisingly
inflexible.
Which they
shouldn't be, right.
It actually should be the opposite
digital and, and, and virtual
environments should be extremely
malleable to the user's needs.
And we are seeing, I think I like
to believe the beginning of this new
era of, of a time when people can,
and we see this in notebooks, right?
You pick how you want to visualize
you, pick how you want to manage
your data, how you want to clean your
data, how you want to get it from
some wild server into your notebook.
Like all of that stuff is a choose
your own adventure type of experience.
And this is like, this is the most
interesting space for accessibility to
arise, and it is more important in my
opinion, to get out of people's way and to
to break down your barriers in how you
allow a modular community to do its thing
than it is about trying to actually solve.
Making everything high contrast, which
you really should aspire to do is how can
we enable people to build the coolest,
possible shit that they can bring in.
Right.
That, that's
interesting.
And yeah, I'm
just really hopeful for that.
Sorry.
I ranted for like five minutes on
this, but it's very exciting to me.
Tony Fast (he/they): That was great.
I mean, like in a lot of ways,
accessibility is one of the last
things to fall in line with Jupyter.
It's a project built on open
standards and open protocols, right?
And we've been adding and adding
standards and protocols to the
ecosystem for a really long time.
And accessibility is one of the last ones,
you know?
And for
me, I personally
identify, like, I love telling
stories with Jupyter notebooks.
Like I implicitly have communication
challenges as a neurodiverse person.
Jupyter notebooks to me
often appear as a cognitive
accessibility tool like implicitly.
I see the notebook as an accessibility
tool for telling stories that I
wouldn't have been able to communicate
otherwise.
And,
yeah, it's fantastic for me, for those reasons.
Frank Elavsky (he/him): Mars had something
interesting to say can I jump on this?
Okay.
Okay,
How do you advocate for cultural shift to
accessibility in a decentralized
space such as open source?
Yes.
This is a very good
question.
If, for
example, needing
approval from some
other, for a grant to hire people
with disabilities,
I feel like there's still some
cultural resistance that technology is
neutral or against,
Oops, sorry,
chat moved.
Or against,
oh, sorry.
I lost my space.
Or against bringing cultural war.
Yeah.
Centralized spaces, such as
companies or governments can
implement top-down policies, the
de-centralized spaces by nature.
Can't do that.
And this is exactly why I'm
glad you asked, because now
I can just say it straight.
This is why I brought in community
organizing as a, just a little hint
that I gave earlier in my talk.
You all should, I don't
want to add to the pressure.
You're all going to be learning
a lot of new things and doing new
things, but your job is to become
organizers in a decentralized space.
How do you get a community together to
fight a slumlord? You organize.
and you can't rely on the police.
You can't rely on the mayor or whatever.
They might be helpful.
Centralized systems are still helpful
when you're in a decentralized like micro
ecosystem, right?
You can
partner with these big things and
sometimes they
can do things for you, muscle things
around, but when you're on the ground
and you're working in a pretty flat space
organized.
And yeah,
organizers have a long and rich history of like
doing some pretty cool things that
I think open-source communities can
learn from.
Because
one of, you know, for example, one of
the things you
can do is you know,
there's cultural resistance that technology is
neutral.
In organizing,
you know, you generally will try
to avoid philosophical debates.
Right?
You'll bring people together
on like, we care about, I care
about this, you care about this.
Right.
Okay, good.
Now that we agree it
let's do it like, and the
debate is you know,
whether intentionally or not, it's one of the
things that, that really slows down.
And being really action oriented
in a decentralized system is
important.
And there's
a space for philosophy and then
there's a space
for deeper discussion and it needs to
happen, but it needs to happen in what
you might call a caucus or a breakout
group of people who you've designated
this as a really safe space to kind
of figure out what we believe in.
And then we go to the
larger community with
just action.
And it takes
a lot of work.
I, I burnt out from community
organizing years ago.
That's why I'm not
doing it.
It is very tiring,
but I learned
a lot of lessons from
that space.
Okay,
Mars,
continuing uncomfortable
talking about advocacy, justice
access and humanities spaces.
Yeah.
I
love the humanities.
worked in
digital humanities before
I got a job in tech.
It's my
undergrad stuff.
I think
in some ways, decentralized is also a benefit.
Over centralized in
terms of changing things.
Centralization.
Yeah.
Lots of bureaucracy.
You gotta be lucky.
I was lucky at Visa.
Just top down.
Nobody fought me.
I was like, let's do this.
They're like, okay.
It's part of the mission.
Sure.
Stamp, stamp, stamp,
stamp go.
That's very rare.
Right.
One centralized
groups reached critical mass.
It can be easier to push forward.
Yeah.
That's exactly what
happened.
Yeah.
Okay.
Larger discussion on this.
We have three minutes.
Anybody else have comments or anything?
Isabela Presedo-Floyd (she/her): I do
think Rose's comment is interesting
because spending all my time in a
de-centralized space does not feel
like it is faster action oriented.
Although I see why it could
seem that way, but go ahead.
Tony Fast (he/they): Sometimes the
open source feels like a parade.
And I'm on the side of it, right.
Where it's like, there are only
certain people who can float
some of these things, you know?
So yeah, it really is a cha I mean,
it's not even just like a decentralized
system, like in the Jupyter, we're
starting to see larger organizations
gather around the project too.
So it's almost like a decentralized
in pseudo centralized philosophies
interfering.
Right.
And
I mean, after hearing you talk to you, I just
want to go start a coup somewhere.
I don't even know where, but like, I'm
just like to go organize something.
Oh no, look, it's tear
down a stop sign somewhere.
Isabela Presedo-Floyd (she/her):
Like, just I'd love if you turn that
energy into people, getting some
code in on, to be honest with you.
Frank Elavsky (he/him): The thing
that I think entices people about
organizing is overthrowing systems of
power, but it turns out that that's a
very small piece, largely organizing
you, go and knock on someone's door.
You check out, you learn your neighbor's name.
You learn what their care
about.
You connect
with them and you're doing almost
no work for a very long time.
It doesn't feel like work, right.
It's a different kind
of work.
And then
eventually when you reach a critical mass
of people and
you all know, they care about the same
thing you do, then boom, you can do an
action.
And if you've
strategized correctly, you can do pretty
amazing things.
So yeah,
Frank Elavsky (he/him): let's go,
Isabela Presedo-Floyd (she/her):
I'm really enjoying the turn.
This has taken.
This is not where I expected to go today.
Frank Elavsky (he/him): The best talk I've ever
given today for sure.
I love it with this way.
Tony Fast (he/him): Yeah.
Mars' picket signs are
going to be the best and I
promise you they're going to be
the most accessible, like on her blog posts.
Like people are like, these are
the most accessible images, so I
can't wait to see how she protests.
Frank Elavsky (he/him): That's awesome.
Yeah.
There's , there's a whole And I'd
love to remain part of that discussion
too, just to be an ear or a fly on
the wall if you will, but there's
a whole unexplored, and by unexplored,
Frank Elavsky (he/him): I don't
mean theoretically people would talk
about this in papers and whatnot, but
there are, there are problems when
it comes to picketing or advocating
in digital spaces, because there
actually is a, a really
immovable inflexible nature,
by which, by how
we've designed, you go to a website,
you can't like protest the website
in the same way that you could.
If you stand outside a building
and say, stop, whatever.
Right.
And so we lose our physical
embodied agency in digital spaces.
And there's this really interesting
thing that happens then in how we
organize.
Yeah, let's
go.
Okay.
So anyway, I'm reading chat again.
Yeah.
I just hope to leave you all with a
sense of passion, that there's tons of
things that different people could do.
If you're interested, you
don't have to write code.
There's a huge space for
just connecting with people.
You need to connect and organize and
congeal around actions you want to take.
And then, you know, you just
want to write code and have
somebody tell you what to do.
And you kind of live in a little like
dungeon box there's roles for those
people too.
Yeah, everybody
has
a space.
And thanks.
Thanks for having me.
This was an enormous
amount of fun, super glad.
Tony Fast (he/they): That's awesome.
Thank you for being
here for that was
Tony Fast (he/they): really informative
and you know, we're going to have
more of these events in the future.
We'll let you know about
them and maybe, you
know, send out some invites to your
colleagues and let's, let's start
getting a crew together, right?
Like organization happens
with a massive amount
of people.
And,
Yeah, it seems like we're all angry in the
same direction, so let's keep.
Isabela Presedo-Floyd (she/her): Right.
And I would also say, thank you
for, I know Tony said, thank
you, but really thank you.
I, I hope that, you know,
you have very rare expertise.
And so I was really happy that you were,
that you were willing to come speak with
us since there's not a lot of people
that I've run into at least doing this.
So I'm super grateful and many
people in the community have asked
for a lot of answers to a lot of
questions you discussed today.
So I think even people who
can't be here, we'll be super
happy to have these resources.
Cool.
Thank you.
Thanks so much.
Tony Fast (he/they):
I also want to credit.
He did very good crowd work today,
which is hard to do in these digital spaces.
Kudos to you, kudos to you.
All
right.
Well Isabela,
Do we need to share this?
So Frank, where we can probably throw you
off stage?
I don't
know if somebody can do that.
Let me get the bucket.
Isabela Presedo-Floyd (she/her): Oh my
gosh, Tony.
Tony Fast (he/they): So do we
need to show our presentation now, Isabela?
Isabela Presedo-Floyd (she/her): Yes.
Let me get that back up for you.
And you can talk if that's okay.
Tony Fast (he/they): That was so good.
I was I'm so happy.
We finally got to see that
Isabela Presedo-Floyd (she/her):
I have been waiting anxiously.
Okay.
Sharing in tire.
It's going to be a moment of awkward.
And then a moment of here we are.
I had it for me.
So I remembered once you stop.
Tony Fast (he/they): Oh, nice.
Nice.
So let's see
Tony Fast (he/they): how many
folks are hanging around here?
We had 10 folks.
Would we think we just do like one
breakout room or two breakout rooms?
Isabela Presedo-Floyd (she/her):
It depends if you want
everyone to talk to you today.
I think 10, 10 could be a lot of
people to talk over each other.
So maybe we should just do two.
So people have lots of
opportunities to speak.
If they want to speak, you don't have to,
just to be clear, you don't have to speak.
You don't have to turn camera on
whatever it prompts you to do.
Tony Fast (he/they): That's
super cool.
Can you do me a favor
and share the
notes document in there?
Isabela Presedo-Floyd (she/her): When I'm
not sharing my screen.
Tony Fast (he/they): Okay.
Yeah.
Good point.
What was
Tony Fast (he/they): it
we're going to talk about?
Isabela Presedo-Floyd (she/her):
Oh, that's the next slide.
Okay, so we have two
prompts.
And of course,
Isabela Presedo-Floyd (she/her): if you
have other things you want to discuss,
that's open too, but so we want to.
How would you have done past
work differently if you already
knew whatever you learned today,
that kind of introspection
reflection, thinking
about those choices can really help you figure
out what you want to do in the future.
And also just what new
questions do you have?
What more do you want to learn?
I've always found it really helpful.
Identifying what, you know, at least for
me, I never stopped having more questions.
So it's kind of like, what
do I want to research next?
Cause you may be in a room with someone
who has an answer to that and we can
already start connecting them together.
And just so you know, once I share the
notes document, these
questions are listed in there as well.
So you don't have to
remember them going to one
breakout rooms.
Frederic had to go.
Let's just
Do, we're gonna Tania.
We'll just start one breakout
room.
And , we'll all
be here to
answer any questions and we'll.
Yeah, we'll
share this document in
that room and we'll just have a little
discussion.
These are
Tony Fast (he/they): your prompts.
Feel
free to jump in with anything else
and let's
just start that session now.
Text: breakout discussions are not recorded
Tony Fast (he/they): All right.
Well, we'll have
to do the summarization
part because we're
all in the same room and thank you all
for participating and bringing your
experiences to the discussion.
We have
a
feedback form,
we'll drop
a link in the chat.
We'd really love some
feedback.
There's
a new platform for us and where we
have three more of these events
scheduled through
March.
So we want to continue to
improve the experience for
everybody.
So please fill
out the
feedback survey.
What's after
Tony Fast (he/they): that one.
I love
these slides.
Yup.
So
next weekend, we're
going to be writing some more image
descriptions for docentation.
Tony Fast (he/they): We're going to
be running some low code exercises.
We'll have some experts around
thinking about some harder
problems in the technology
stack for
Jupyter.
So the next
week is largely going
to be a breakout room, more of a working
session.
And then
in March, we're going to have another
pair of events.
We'll have another featured
speaker.
We haven't,
I haven't heard anything about that yet.
We have another future speaker
and then we'll have another set
of breakout rooms and workshops
again.
So in the meantime we have
Jupyter accessibility
meetings.
every other Wednesday
you can find them on the Jupyter community
calendar.
So that's
another place for us to stay
involved.
If you want
Tony Fast (he/they): to learn more
about what the community's doing, if you
want to possibly probably see some data
visualizations we've got
the Jupyter monthly
community call which is
happening, I believe in
two weeks.
Our accessibility
work happens on the Jupyter
Discourse and the Jupyter
accessibility repository.
And please join
us at a Jupyter Lab, bi-weekly Jupyter
lab, accessibility meeting sometimes
some time.
Yeah, so that's the ongoing
community stuff and things you can act on.
We'd love to see some of your
faces again.
Is there
another site.
And thank you.
Thank you to me, Tony.
Now, thank you to Isabela and
Tania for doing all of the
legwork.
This was
a long event to get
together.
We,
Tony Fast (he/they): thought there
were a lot of important features
that we needed to have with it.
So thank God.
Thank goodness.
They're
happening now.
We have
to thank Bloomberg and AWS
and NumFocus for
the support on
these events.
We have
to thank the Jupyter community building
team Ana and Christine,
,our sponsors which with
Bloomberg, NumFocus, AWS.
And thanks
to the team that wrote the event
proposal.
This was
Actually originally
going to be run by some, by some folks
and it was accepted before the pandemic.
So some of the delay in getting
here was re-
thinking
about the workshop
differently so that we could do it
digitally.
And last
Tony Fast (he/they): but not least, thanks
to Frank, for
being
here and good luck
with your PhD, man.
You're doing really great work.
It's exciting to read
your future research.