Tony Fast (he/they): That's fun.
Oh man.
I was just about to tell you about my
recent accessibility, recent accessibility
problem that I had myself, my wife,
she got a delicious box of macaroons.
See, they came in a lot of colors.
Now I keep calling this again.
Because I have to look at the color
sheet and guess which color is which and
what flavor it is, but I'm colorblind.
So I think I keep accidentally
eating the ones that my wife wants
to eat, just because I don't know
what colors are, but it's a fun game.
Nonetheless.
I wish there were some more tech, if
they have more sprinkles on them, I'd be
able to tell something a little bit more.
Isabela Presedo-Floyd (she/her): Right.
Or I wonder if there's something
they could learn from like, right.
Don't some pies do like,  they have
like different dough shapes on top too?
Like there's different things like that.
I wonder how that would work with
that pastry, but yeah, that's a,
that's a really good,  example
of an inaccessible experience.
Tony Fast (he/they): You know, if I was
allergic to any of the things, it would be
really living life on the edge situation.
Oh my God.
It's the second event.
Oh, how cool.
I can't believe we got here.
Isabela Presedo-Floyd (she/her):
Yeah, but we did.
And it's exciting.
I'm excited at least.
Tony Fast (he/they): Yeah.
We'll get started in what, like
another minute or two,  let folks
roll in on their sleepy Saturday.
Yeah, it looks like we got a big
crew already eight folks, and to
all the west coast people, God
bless you for being up so early.
Isabela Presedo-Floyd (she/her): I
always wonder what I'm never quite
sure what the threshold for early is.
Like, I feel like I know the extremes.
If someone said to me 4:00 AM,
I would be like, that's early.
And if someone's at noon, I would
be like, that's probably not
early anymore, because it's
not technically morning, but in
between that, I'm not really sure
Tony Fast (he/they): Why don't we
celebrate people like making it till noon?
Like nobody's never like making it
the lunch break, you know, I think
we just need to start celebrating
smaller wins as we go along.
Well, cool.
What do you say
We kick off that presentation
and we get,  folks working
together and impacting open source?
Isabela Presedo-Floyd (she/her):
Sounds good.
Do you want to introduce yourself
quickly first though, right.
Tony Fast (he/they): Oh, I don't
know how to do my own alt texts.
Hi, I'm Tony fast.
Isabela will
insert my alt text later on.
But  welcome to
the accessibility matters.
I'll moderate, but this is Isabela's deal.
So I'm going to let her
go and do the intro.
Isabela Presedo-Floyd (she/her): Yes.
That was a good one.
I'm Isabela Presedo-Floyd.
My pronouns are she/her.
And in terms of my alt text, or
what I look like, I'm a Latina woman
who's wearing all kinds of pink
and orange stripes today and has
untamable black curly hair.
Tony also has untamable hair
except it's blonde and really cool,
like kind of a mohawk sometimes.
And yeah.
Tony Fast (he/they): I love
that you think it's blonde.
It's different colors and it is
anything else, but we'll go with it.
I think I'm going to one day, I
want my alt texts to include silver fox.
Isabela Presedo-Floyd (she/her): Oh,
no, that deserves a sip of tea.
Okay.
Well, welcome to our
second workshop today.
We're going to be talking about
writing image descriptions for
documentation also, depending on
interest automated tests for ensuring
that things like image descriptions,
which are very easy to test, are like
checked for when people are making PR.
And we're going to be taking action
today and helping you contribute to
Jupyter projects to help this out.
So let's get started if
this will work, please.
Okay.
There we go.
Tony Fast (he/they): It's
definitely going to work.
We've run this event many times.
Isabela Presedo-Floyd (she/her):
I have keyboard problems.
That's the problem.
Go on.
So should we add this presentation to the
stream is that what we should
do if you want to, I'll give
people reminders real quick.
So first by attending this event, you are
agreeing to follow the code of conduct.
You definitely clicked a box if
you made it this far on the ticket
list, but that's just your reminder.
And also this event will be recorded.
It's already being reported and posted
publicly, at least the main session parts.
We won't be doing the breakout rooms.
So that's just.
And yeah.
Tony, why don't you welcome people
to your favorite planet in the solar system?
Tony Fast (he/they): Oh my God.
Welcome to planet Jupyter.
We're so happy to have
you orbiting it today.
So oh man, we didn't set
up our polls today, but we should
definitely get a poll going about
how new folks are to,  Jupyter.
But yes, welcome to,
the world's most favorite
interactive computing environment.
A lot of us have been able to
benefit, oh my God, this is Dirty.
This is my, this is my puppy.
If you don't, if you take
away anything from this event,
learn that having puppies in your
presentations makes them better.
If you're a cat person,
cats and dogs, that's fine.
But,  Jupyter is a place
for humans to interactive compute,
Dirty is not too great at the keys.
But right now,
any,  disabled humans.
Might be kept away from
working on Jupyter.
So that's why we're all here to
help improve that experience.
You'll find tons of people in
different domains, in different
disciplines using Jupyter, and we're
all here to make sure that everybody can
benefit the way that others have so far.
Isabela Presedo-Floyd (she/her): Yeah.
And definitely to add to that, Jupyter
has a lot of different projects if
you're not familiar for not just a
file type interface or, you know,
even single community sometimes.
It's a pretty big place.
If you're new here.
Welcome.
Tony Fast (he/they): And if you're an,
if you start hearing words and brands
and things, that sound like band names,
and you're not sure what it is, feel
free to drop a link in the chat and
we'll try and send you some links.
Jupyter does have
a pretty big universe.
Accessibility's a small
but impactful part of it.
So we'd like to make sure that you
all find your place in the Jupyter.
Isabela Presedo-Floyd (she/her):
And just to continue defining
what it is, what is accessibility?
Accessibility is making sure that we
are building things that can be used
by a full range of human experiences.
So what that means in practice is
making sure that we put the needs
of people with disabilities first.
Right?
Cause those are the people that usually
aren't a part of these processes.
And are, you know, kept away from
being able to do the things that
they need to do and really should
be able to do like the rest of us.
So this could be anything like this could
be a really wide ranging thing today.
We're actually going to be talking
about web accessibility, probably
bringing up WCAG or the Web Content
Accessibility Guidelines at some point,
which are the guidelines that
help us have a common language and
make decisions about what needs to be
done to get started with this kind of work.
Also accessibility is for everyone.
I talked a little bit at the last
workshop about curb cuts, which are
in like the curb for a sidewalk.
It's that ramp that you have.
So we had a little discussion
about what curb cuts are for
that I have summarized for you.
So they were made initially right,
for wheelchair users, but you can
also use them if you're using a cart
or moving things for any reason.
Or you have a baby buggy, you
need to drive around. Skateboards
bikes, all kinds of cool things.
Tony was talking about doing
cool tricks on curb cuts before.
So, right.
Even though this is something that
was made specifically for disabled
people, this really does serve everyone.
And it serves a lot of the
times in unexpected ways.
So this is often used as a metaphor.
For all kinds of
accessibility efforts, right.
That if you center it around needs
of disabled people, that doesn't mean
you're only designing it for them,
that it's actually going to benefit
more than you probably anticipated.
Accessibility is also cross project.
This is really important in Jupyter
because there's a lot of things
under the Jupyter umbrella, right?
The Jupyter ecosystem has a lot
of different subprojects, and
this is not a single problem of
just one project versus the other.
This also means we need to be considering
things all the way from the notebook
file to the many different interfaces
to documentation and more, and of
course, documentation is what we'll be
working on today, but more on that more.
Because accessibility
is happening now, right?
We have these events, but they are
not the only accessibility efforts.
We have ongoing some
highlights from the last year.
We've also right,
we've had regular meetings around this for
a year, which has been great for bringing
in new people for collecting people across
projects that have an interest in this
and getting them a chance to community.
This has also grown our community.
So that means we've had totally
new people that I haven't met in
Jupyter spaces before come in.
We've had people get involved in projects.
They haven't before we've had some
audits of multiple projects based on.
That I mentioned earlier
with related issues and PRS.
So we can keep track of this work and
have a better sense of what needs to
be done and not just this nebulous,
it's an accessible kind of statement.
And we have CZI Essential Open
Source Software for Science.
We have a grant to further, Jupyter's
accessibility in the next two years,
which is really exciting to be able to.
You know, devoted funding for that.
So we're not just relying on volunteers
because as great as they are, and the
amazing work that they've done, this
is a really big project. And some goals
that we have going forward that we
haven't done yet adding automated tests.
This is really important for open source.
So we can't guarantee who is going to
review any contribution at any given moment.
We need to make sure the notebook file
format is accessible as can be right?s
There's a lot of projects here,
but pretty much all of them
interact with the notebook file.
And so do a lot of external,
like non-Jupyter projects.
So that foundational level is critical.
We'll also be updating, improving
documentation, and maybe I lied a
little, these aren't just future goals.
Two of these are today's goals, right?
Updating, improving documentation
and getting you involved.
Woo.
Get excited for that.
Tony Fast (he/they): You're so sneaky.
So sneaky last week you use the same
slide and you're like, oh, we're not
going to do nothing today, but sit down
this week, you're gonna and make us work.
Isabela Presedo-Floyd (she/her):
I try for continuity.
If we have any people who have
been to both events, I have fun.
Yeah.
Going to segue a little bit.
That is right.
Documentation has images, almost always.
That's been my experience, definitely
many of the Jupyter docs do, but what
happens if you can't access them?
Whether that's because you can't see
them, the link, you know, you have a bad
internet connection and it doesn't load.
It's a broken link.
You're going to get something like this.
You're going to get some kind of icon
that like says there's no image and
you'll probably get a description
that's the file name.
Like image dot PNG.
Man.
I wish I knew it image.
That was, huh.
That's not a helpful description at all.
So this is actually one of the most
common WCAG failures that we've listed.
This is,  by the WebAIM Million,
which is a project that takes the
top million webpages on the internet.
And
accessibility analysis over them.
So missing alternative text for images
is actually the second, most common
failure for multiple years in a row.
So as simple as this seems, it's
actually a really big problem.
Okay.
This is something we're not catching.
Right?
Right.
Now I know we have Jupyter docs that
don't have this and then open source.
This might be how
automated tests could help.
So this is kind of the why for
what we're doing today, right?
This is the problem.
And we have kind of these potential
solutions to make sure our
community has a commitment to do
better, but backing up, backing up.
I said all these words, and I
didn't really tell you what an image
description is in the first place.
Right?
So here we have an image.
And if it's not there, it's going to
say, this is the planet Jupyter, right?
Tony Fast (he/they): You
spelled Jupyter wrong.
This always, I just want to find
the results that I need.
Isabela Presedo-Floyd (she/her): Yeah.
That's, that's kind of a running joke.
We have, you know, selling Jupyter
becomes a real problem when you're
in this community for too long.
No matter how I spelled
Jupyter, it looks wrong to me.
Yeah.
But with this, right?
There's so many types of images.
And similarly, there's a lot of
different types of alt texts.
So running through that really
quickly, there's a few major types
we're going to talk about today.
That there's more, and this is from
the W3C's tutorial about this.
so I can link that later.
If you want more information.
One type is an informative image.
So say I'm reading a blog
post and it says, puppies know
how to make emotional appeal.
And then we have this picture of a dog.
It would make sense to say, right.
A fluffy puppy looking at
the camera with big eyes.
Okay.
How the puppy is looking, right,
that it's cute.
And has big eyes is relevant
to the rest of the content.
Right?
It makes sense.
It doesn't just make sense to say
a dog afterwards, so to speak.
It doesn't have the emphasis as the image.
Tony Fast (he/they): What about, what
about if I was to do something like "Dawww?"
Is that informative, or?
Isabela Presedo-Floyd (she/her): I'm
always really unsure, to be honest.
I don't know if you're making
a joke or asking me seriously.
Yeah.
I took it too seriously, but yeah,
I've actually seen discussion around
that where people are talking about,
you know, how much emotion and
personality is appropriate in alt text.
This is probably a larger discussion,
but when I would be happy to have,
once we get past the baseline,
We also have functional images.
So right.
Say this is a button here
with this trashcan on it.
You wouldn't call it though.
A trash can because what the
button actually does is to delete.
So this might also be the case for
logos on home pages of websites, that
kind of thing, where you're trying
to describe what happens when you
interact with that image, because many
images are used in that kind of way.
There's also complex.
This is from the Jupyter docs
actually, and it's way too small for
you to see easily on these slides.
I don't have a single good
alt text recommendation for
this that would fit neatly.
So there's kind of a few guidelines
I use for complex images though,
right?
You go from general to specific, right?
You want to kind of give people a
sense of any titles, any layout.
Before going into the smaller details and
describe any key information or trends.
That's something that comes up a lot
if you're working with graphs. You also
want to make sure if there's any text in
the image, as there's a lot here, it needs
to be outside of the image somewhere.
There's a few options for
how you can do that, right.
It could just be in the
rest of the content.
It could be actually linked somewhere.
And what I mean by you may want to
link out is that alt text is not
intended to be too long, right?
So you may want to link to an external
kind of record of that, whether that's,
you know, a paragraph later on the
same page, or if you have a lot of
complex images, maybe you have some
kind of footnote system, but this
would be a lot to read through at once.
If you're just trying to go through them.
The final type I want to talk
about today is decorative images.
So once again, we're back on that
blog post about the dogs and I, the
post now says my mother will be happy
to know her dog is in my slides.
And then we just keep talking, right?
The heart here, doesn't
really add content.
It's just kind of there.
And so what you're going to
do is leave the tag empty.
You do still need the tag
because that lets assistive
technology know that this isn't.
Is, you know, it gives it something
to do with this image instead of
jutt read the image name, but empty
all text is actually an option.
The thing that we don't want is to
have no text or to have alt texts.
That's just the image name, which
is how some things automated.
On text styling, just
a few quick pointers, too.
We do want to spell things correctly.
You can totally write this and
something with a spell check
and then copy and paste it in.
I definitely, there are words
I don't have confidence spelling myself.
We want to have punctuation just like
anything else that helps navigate
sentence, case capitalization as
exemplified here just means the start of
the sentences, capitalized and proper.
Now.
And we only have consistent
naming for repeated elements.
This can get really important
in documentation, right?
Where if you have like step-by-step
images, you don't want to call like
something, a menu and one image
and then called the same thing,
like a pop-up and another image.
Right.
That would be really confusing
if you can't see that they're
the same thing for some reason.
So that's something we'll
probably be dealing with today.
And this is something
you'll hear me say a lot.
It's all about context.
So whenever you're in doubt, a lot
of the time working in these spaces,
the alt text paths have not been as
clear as say when you're like writing,
you know, a recipe or a blog post.
And you're like, oh,
that's a picture of soup.
Oh, that's a picture of a dog.
But what really matters is
thinking about how this
fits in the whole.
So reading the paragraphs before
and after, what kind of image is
the author expecting you to get?
Or what kind of information is the author
expecting you to get from this image?
Making sure that if the image
doesn't render, you could break
the link and test it yourself.
Does the whole thing still makes
sense without it? Those are some
good tests which we'll get to
try out a little later today.
And just more to advocate for this.
We're talking about this in Jupyter,
but it's a good skill for every
planet everywhere you go on the web.
Right?
Alt text is not a Jupyter problem.
So even if you're new to
Jupyter, don't worry at all.
This is totally a skill
that you can use here.
You can take with you and start making
sure that this is less of a failure
for these future accessibility audits.
So, yeah.
I think, for me that's work time.
Unless we want to take questions first.
I, up to you, Tony, what do you think
is wise here? I talked for a while.
Tony Fast (he/they): Oh, I
think that you did so great.
Right?
And it is an interplanetary
problem, right?
Like the NumPy team is on Mars.
There's alt text on Mars.
Mars, and Jupyter covered.
Great.
So we've got eight people
and I think we've run this
event with eight people before.
So I think we just go into one
big old breakout room and we all
spend this Saturday together.
Learning about alt text and context.
Note: Sprint discussions are not recorded.
Isabela Presedo-Floyd (she/her): Of
course, I'm going to say it once more.
The point of this is just to celebrate.
I really am impressed by the amount of
work that you all did today, and you
tackled some really difficult images
or you tackled some simple images,
but thought very critically about
them and about what their meaning was.
And should they be there at all?
I, it makes me so happy to hear
people having these conversations
because I really don't enough.
Yeah, if we can go. (singing) Will the
slides respond to my keyboard?
It's always a mystery.
Tony Fast (he/they): I
just found the,
I just found the answer to one of
Gabriel's questions, ARIA labeled,
by let you say that a paragraph,
or ARIA described by lets you
say that a paragraph describes.
So, if we get add linking to this,
then we'd be able to do stuff like
that, where you could say, Hey,
this paragraph has an ID and now
the ARIA described by this ID.
Yeah, I saw that.
And then I gave up, well, I didn't, I was
like, I'll have to look at this later.
Cause I don't know how to add IDs in RST.
So, you know.
Isabela Presedo-Floyd (she/her): Yeah.
That's what happens.
I've found a lot of this
workshop is like, what can we do?
You know, the suggestions in this
time and our knowledge of how this
system works has been kind of limited,
but yeah, it's definitely still
helpful to be thinking about it.
Like we started them.
One more thing I want to say
we do have a feedback survey, so
you can give us any information.
This is basically just so we know if
anything went wrong, if there's anything
you really like to be done differently,
because we do have two more of these
events you'll hear about in the moment.
This is just making sure that
we're creating events that
actually are helping you.
That is the point of this.
So it'd be great to have your feedback.
I believe it's five or six questions and
some, several of them are not required.
So totally up to you.
And I can link that in the chat after.
Other thing.
I just mentioned upcoming events.
We have two more, one more speaker and
one more sprint coming up in March 2022.
I haven't put the dates here
because I want to be quadruple sure
before putting that information
somewhere that could confuse you.
They are coming soon and we
do have some stuff scheduled.
I'm really excited about it.
As much as I keep my lips closed.
The one thing I will say
too, with the sprint, we are
still open with sprint ideas.
If there is anything that you are
really passionate about learning with
the accessability stuff, I am happy
to hear suggestions with that because
there's multiple things we can do.
And it's still far enough that
if you have something that you'd
really like to hear about, I would
rather be doing something home.
So, yeah, that is going to be exciting
to keep up to date with this too.
There will be another Jupyter blog post.
I'm not sure how I'll be found this, which
will then mean it is also on Twitter,
but beyond the Jupyter Discourse,
those will be the main venues that
I would follow to keep up with this.
Can you think of any others, Tony, that
you think it will be advertised on?
Tony Fast (he/they): No,
but you can join the community call this week.
There'll probably be another
community call next month.
There's a bunch of community calls.
So we hope to see folks around.
Yeah.
Isabela Presedo-Floyd (she/her): Yeah.
That's this slide is, there are a
few ways you can get involved in the
meantime. The first is community calls.
That's what Tony mentioned.
It's basically a cross-project
show and tell once a month.
It's in the last Tuesday of every month.
So that does mean there is one
this Tuesday, you can find it on
the Jupyter community calendar.
We'll have it in your time
zone and with relevant links.
If you haven't been to one
before, I would recommend just
showing up, but you are also always
free to share anything you want.
I would say Jupyter related, but I you're
even open if you're like, oh, I did this
cool thing on one project and I thought
it might interest you all to happen here.
Like we're pretty open there.
It's just about making sure that everybody
is celebrating and communicating.
If you want to get involved with
Jupyter accessibility efforts
specifically, there is a topic on
the Jupyter discourse for this.
You can find what people
are already talking about.
And we have a Jupyter accessibility,
GitHub repo, which is kind of the
center for coordinating cross project.
That's why I point people there
first, because each project kind
of has its own things going on.
You can also join a JupyterLab,
accessibility meeting.
It is JupyterLab, but,  we have some,
for example, I'm always in that meeting.
And so I'm happy to
talk about other things.
It's mostly just JupyterLab because
that's the people that we had that had.
But we're totally open to discussing
accessibility on a wider scale there,
because most of the problems we
have per project are problems in all
projects and we should help each other.
And finally, I have some thank you is
because this has been a big process
running these events, Tony and Tania in
particular have helped me run this event.
I don't know what I would do without
Tania's tech support and just general.
event wrangling knowledge, as well as Tony has so
much experience with event coordinating.
And I really don't think this would have
been possible without either of them.
You also have the Jupyter community
building committee,  Ana and Christine
were two of my points of contact for
this making sure that we had all the
Goa heads and funding for speakers.
The Jupyter community workshops
sponsors, or how we tie into that
community building committee.
So thank you to them.
NumFocus is also part of this
whole coordination, and I really
appreciate that too. They're,
similarly, part of the sponsors.
And we have a team that originally
about this wrote this event
proposal, because these events.
I have been a long time coming.
People have been wanting this.
A lot of people have really been trying
to push for Jupyter accessibility, and I
want to acknowledge that that effort came
before me and I'm grateful that they did
it and that we can have these events now.
So thank you! Anything
you'd like to add, Tony?
514s
Tony Fast (he/they): Thank you.
Thanks.
Isabela Presedo-Floyd (she/her):
Thank you.